hey everyone welcome back to our Channel
I am back with another interesting topic
in the tosa automation
playlist now uh we are going to discuss
about a genuine problem which you will
certainly come across whenever you're
are trying to automate any application
now tosa or any other automation tool is
uh very efficient in automating or in uh
scanning the elements which are web-
based applications right but what about
the desktop based applications or um
within your application you have some
desktop elements uh which you need to
automate right so what do you do in
these kind of scenarios or in your
application certain elements are not
being identified by tosa and you need to
perform some action on those particular
Elements which are not showing up while
scanning the application right so all of
these issues are very common whenever
you are working on an automation project
no matter what the application is or no
matter which project you are working on
so on a scale of 1 to 10 you will always
face this issues nine out of 10 times
okay so you have to uh be aware of all
the possible solutions which are
possible um especially in tosa okay so
you would know that when tosa is not
able to identify some elements then you
have to create custom controls but that
is not always the first solution so that
option should be your last option
because you don't want to end up um
writing code for your uh custom controls
right that would be a difficult option
to choose rather you use all the
features of TOs
to try and solve this particular issue
before moving on to last option which is
creating a custom control by using the
net libraries so I'm going to show you a
particular example where tosa is not
able to identify certain elements but
there is a work around so let's see how
we can move around this particular
problem so I have opened up uh my device
manager okay so this is present uh in
your control panel so as you can see uh
this is a Windows window based control
right so this is part of the Microsoft
Windows and uh everything inside this is
window based so it's not a web based
interface okay so here um if I go into
monitors and generate PNP monitor I go
into properties okay so it opens up a
new window here you can see this window
and then um if I go into details tab
okay there is um the property and then
value okay and in the property is a
drop- down right now um what if my
automation task is to uh verify all the
values which are present in this
dropdown okay and I have to do this
using tosa so let's see whether tosa is
able to identify all the elements on
this particular window-based control
right now remember that uh tosa supports
most of the Technologies including the
desktop based application so it should
be able to identify these elements okay
but let's see whether it is able to
actually do that so I will go to modules
I will go and do the scan
application okay so I can see both the
windows here uh the device manager as
well as the generic PNP
monitor now um in some cases if you're
not able to scan that particular
application if no element is showing up
when you scan this particular window
then you can fall back upon other
options okay so right click uh on on
here you can see when X is selected
which means it is a window based control
um and then you have other options like
Vision Ai and then UIA okay so these two
options are still there uh if you are
not able to scan with the default option
which is the win X option okay but for
now we will go with the V next
option so I'm going to scan this
particular application and now you can
see it is showing up some elements okay
but let's see if uh it is able to scan
the elements which I require
okay so now I can see a label generic
PNP monitor property combo box value
list okay cancel tab control so it is
showing up most of the elements but I
need the drop- down elements inside this
because I need to verify them okay so I
can see the property and the combo box
right but I'm not able to see the
elements inside the combo box um so my
next action would be to increase the
filtered items and try to see if it is
showing up any
particular uh combo box items here okay
and as you can see so this is the
details Tab and currently it is not
showing me any elements under the combo
box okay so it is showing up some other
elements in some other tabs but not in
this particular tab
okay and this is a problem now because
uh my job is to verify the properties
which are displayed here right and uh I
cannot do it directly uh after scanning
this particular
control so uh let's go ahead and let's
select the combo box okay so it is
unique uh we can go ahead with the
properties which can uh identify the
this combo box okay so what we will do
is now we will go ahead and save this
module and now we will go back to our
module okay so this is the
module okay and then we have the combo
box here
right now in order to get the elements
which are inside the combo box okay so
if we look at this application there are
lots of properties which are present
right and since these are not being
displayed currently in the scan engine
what we can do is we can add a generic
element so what we are going to do is uh
in the combo box right we will right
click and then uh we will go to this
three
ellipses and there you will find create
generic list item okay so this is a
generic type which can be added for a
combo box uh it is a list item type okay
so it will identify any list items which
are present once we create this generic
list item or once we add this particular
property which is the create generic
list item okay so once we add this now
you will see that it is added under
combo box and it is a item right now
interestingly if you go to the
properties of this item
uh you can see the engine is when X
right but uh the explicit name actually
contains all the different items which
we are looking for okay so as you can
see it has got all the properties which
are present in my
application okay so I can actually
select any particular item using this
explicit name okay so now what I will do
is we will add a test case folder here
and we will call it win
controls okay and then we will add a
test case here we'll say
verify driver
properties and then we will add the
module right here okay now as you can
see it has got a combo box and it has
also got a list item which is a generic
type okay um and we have added this um
manually it was not added by tosa so now
um I can actually select any particular
item using the explicit names you can
see all the item names are present here
which you want to verify okay so uh I
want to verify the device
description so the combo box action mode
will change to select here the device
description is still input I will uh
make it verify and then I will say exist
equals equals
true okay similarly I can verify some
more um capabilities right and then
status okay so these three I want to
verify I will put verify
here and same I will do exist equals
equals
true now an interesting thing to note
here is you will see that um as we keep
on adding the items still uh the item
will get created here and that is
because of the cardinality which is set
to 0 to n okay so now we have done some
verifications let's go ahead and let's
let's execute this test case and let's
see it is able to verify or not
okay so um as you can see it maximized
this particular window right um and if I
go back to tosa let
me make this into a normal window and
then if I look at the log info you can
see the verification was successful for
all the three items in the combo box
okay so this is how you can add generic
list item to your combo box even if
these items are not scanned in the first
instance by tosa and you cannot see them
in the module you can still add it as a
module attribute and once you add this
generic list item as a module attribute
then you'll be able to see all the items
uh which are present in your application
and then you can perform all the
verifications or validations which you
want to perform on this list items okay
so this is one example of how you can
get around these problems when tosa is
not able to scan all the elements on
your application or you're working with
Windows based controls so similarly you
can work around some generic items which
are already present uh when you go into
into your module properties but uh it is
not the case with all the controls okay
and some cases tosa has not provided
these generic items and you need to
create custom controls if these generic
items are not already present and you
cannot add them using uh the properties
of a particular element
right so uh in those cases you have to
uh fall back upon on your last option
which is creating a custom
control that's all for this particular
video if you have any questions then
please leave it in the comments if you
like this video then please subscribe to
our Channel thanks for watching and I
will see you in the next video